Okay so today's דף daf is כ"ט. Chaf Tes. Wow דף daf
29, the last דף daf in the third פרק. perek. With this
we wrap up, well, the first two פרקים perakim which were the
whole focus on being טמא tamei and entering into the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, which we've discussed a few times what I think it's
doing in this מסכת. masechet. And this פרק, perek, I think, is
about the קרבן, korban, you know, and I think it is about
the קרבן korban that somebody brings when they make an oath and
then they violate it בשוגג, beshogeg, either in the future or in
the past. But what we've also seen so far is that it
really lays down the basic parameters about, you know, about what types
of oaths are binding. The difference between a שבועה shevua and a
נדר, neder, שבועה חלה על שבועה, shevua chala al shevua, מושבע ועומד,
mushba ve'omed, אין שבועה חלה על שבועה, ein shevua chala al shevua,
יצא מושבע ועומד, yatza mushba ve'omed, if you try to take a
שבועה shevua to be מבטל את המצווה. mevatel es ha-mitzvah. So it
basically, you know, laid down some of the foundational aspects in the
context of discussing the קרבן. korban. After this פרק, perek, we're really
going to focus on what שבועות Shevuos is doing in סדר נזיקין,
Seder Nezikin, which is the use of oaths within the context of
court deliberations, you know, and the cases and, you know, two litigants
and so on, where it won't all be about the idea of
how an
oath, sort of like, when is
it binding, an oath on top of another oath and those types
of questions, but more about like when is one... there will be
elements of that, but there's also when is one side entitled to
impose an oath on another. What if somebody doesn't take the oath,
do they have to pay? You know, sort of its use as
a tool within the context of the courts. That'll be starting tomorrow.
But anyway, today we wrap up this discussion of שבועות shevuos and
what, you know, different types of שבועה shevua and are they sort
of like valid, do you bring a קרבן, korban, are they meaningful,
and so on. So let's take a look now at the משנה
Mishnah on כ"ט עמוד א'. Chaf Tes Amud Alef. איזהי שבועת שווא?
Eizehi shevuas shav? So we discussed a שבועת ביטוי, shevuas bituy, which
is certainly future-oriented, and then if you violated it בשוגג beshogeg you
bring a קרבן, korban, if you violated it במזיד bemezid you get
lashes. We discussed a past-oriented שבועה, shevua, which if it's... you do
it במזיד, bemezid, it's a שבועת שקר. shevuas sheker. If you violate
a past-oriented שבועה shevua בשוגג, beshogeg, and we discussed what would constitute
שוגג, shogeg, then that's the debate of רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva and
רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, do you bring a קרבן korban for something
that's past-oriented?
That was a שבועת ביטוי shevuas bituy and a שבועת שקר. shevuas
sheker. So the one thing we haven't discussed is a שבועת שווא.
shevuas shav. לא תשבעו בשמי לשקר. Lo sishavu bishmi lasheker. No, that's
לשקר. lasheker.
Yes, yes, which was quoted earlier. Okay, לא תשא את שם ה'
אלהיך לשוא, Lo sisa es shem Hashem Elokecha lashav, do not take
the Lord's name in vain. Okay, so what is to take in
vain as opposed to be false? Okay, so let's take a look.
איזהי שבועת שווא? Eizehi shevuas shav? What is a שבועת שווא, shevuas
shav,
a שבועה shevua taken in vain? נשבע לשנות את הידוע לאדם. Nishba
lishanos es hayaduah l'adam.
You take an oath to claim something is different when it's well
known to people to be different than what
it
is well known to be. Okay, אמר על עמוד של אבן שהוא
של זהב. Amar al amud shel even shehu shel zahav.
You have a pillar of stone and you take an oath that
it's gold. So you might have said that's שבועת שקר, shevuas sheker,
but the point is is that something that is transparently false, now
we'll go with transparently false, we'll modify that when we get to
the גמרא, Gemara, you know, then it's just in vain. You're not
fooling anybody. So is it a lie? Yeah, but there's some sense
of a lie is a lie that actually, you know, works as
a lie. Okay, when it doesn't work as a lie, it's just
in vain. ועל איש שהוא אישה ועל אישה שהיא איש, Ve'al ish
shehu ishah ve'al ishah shehi ish, about a man that's a woman
and about a woman that's a man. Okay, right,
this was obviously a case where they had very gender binary. I
mean, if you had somebody that was intersex and an אנדרוגינוס, androgynos,
that would not be necessarily... anyway. נשבע על דבר שאי אפשר לו.
Nishba al davar she'efshar lo. Now, before we go on, what's missing
from this is something that is transparently true, which gets said elsewhere,
right? But if you say, if you take an oath that two
plus two is five, that's a שבועת שווא, shevuas shav, it's not
שקר, sheker, you're not fooling anybody. If you take an oath that
two plus two is four, it's also a שבועת שווא shevuas shav
because it's completely obvious and the שבועה shevua serves no purpose. Okay,
so it's interesting that's not mentioned in the משנה, Mishnah, but that
is assumed elsewhere that that's included in שבועת שווא. shevuas shav.
Doesn't that mean something that you know, but there's different gradations, like,
you know, there's something patently obvious to everyone else,
but not to you.
Right, we're going to get to that.
We're going to get to how obvious it has to be. Okay,
now, נשבע על דבר שאי אפשר לו. Nishba al davar she'efshar lo.
If you swear about something that was impossible. For example, what would
be a case of impossible?
Low meaning to you or low meaning to...
well, let's take a look. The case is you make a claim
about something that happened to you and it's impossible. So that's what
the relevance of the לא lo there is. אם לא ראיתי גמל
פורח באוויר. Im lo ra'iti gamal poreach ba'avir. I take an oath
if I haven't seen a camel flying in the sky. So obviously
you didn't, so now the question is, but what exactly was your
oath? That sounds like you're making it conditional on something. Why is
it a שבועת שווא? shevuas shav? So we'll figure that out in
the גמרא. Gemara. But the point is it has something to do
with something that's obviously impossible. ואימלו... Ve'im lo...
I did not see a snake as big and as thick as
the beam used in the, you know, olive press. I don't know
if you've ever seen those beams, but they're like enormous. Okay, so
אמר לעדים, amar l'edim, now, we'll
see, we'll discuss this in the גמרא Gemara because even if we
assume that it was impossible, where is the, what's the שבועה shvua
part of this thing that you said? Now, אמר לעדים בואו והעידוני,
amar l'edim bou v'heiduni, you say to witnesses, this is obviously this
is going to be a lead-in to the next פרק perek which
is going to be שבועת העדות, shvuat ha'edus, using a שבועה shvua
as a means of getting somebody to come testify for you, okay,
so you say to witnesses come testify for me, שבועה שלא נעידכם,
shvua shelo na'idchem, we take an oath, no, we won't testify for
you. Now, that's different than a שבועה shvua that we don't know
the testimony, that's שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edus denying their knowledge of the
facts, okay, that's, that's, but this is a שבועה shvua that they
won't, they know it and they won't actually come and testify. So
that actually is a שבועה לבטל את המצווה. shvua l'vatel es hamitzvah.
Okay, they have an obligation to come and testify, they're acknowledging that
they know the facts and they're not going to, they're swearing they're
not, that's a שבועה לבטל את המצווה. shvua l'vatel es hamitzvah. Okay,
or just more directly, נשבע לבטל את המצווה, nishba l'vatel es hamitzvah,
somebody takes an oath not to do a מצווה, mitzvah, שלא לעשות
סוכה ושלא ליטול לולב ושלא להניח תפילין, shelo la'asot sukka v'shelo litol
lulav v'shelo l'haniach tfillin,
okay, all those cases of straight clear ritual מצוות, mitzvos, זו היא
שבועת שווא. zo hi shvuat shav.
No, no, no, that's interesting. שלא לעשות סוכה shelo la'asot sukka means,
it doesn't say שלא לישב.
shelo leishev. Right, so that's actually, so Michael makes an interesting point
which the גמרא Gemara does not discuss, but some of the אחרונים
acharonim do. Why does it say שלא לעשות סוכה? shelo la'asot sukka?
You don't have an obligation to do a סוכה. sukka. Leads to
the נצי"ב Netziv developing a whole idea that is עשיית סוכה asiyat
sukka the הכשר מצווה hachshar mitzvah whole approach of the נצי"ב, Netziv,
הכשר מצווה הכתוב בתורה hachshar mitzvah hakatuv b'Torah because the תורה Torah
says חג הסוכות תעשה לך chag hasukkot ta'aseh lecha from which we
learn that there's an idea to make a סוכה sukka even though
technically you don't have to, right? I can, somebody, you know, if
you grew up in a family or whatever the dad made the
סוכה, sukka, everybody else dwelled in it, right? The kids even if
they were בר מצווה bar mitzvah maybe they helped the dad, maybe
they didn't, they were off playing football or watching TV or whatever
they were doing, right? So they still fulfill your מצווה mitzvah if
you don't make a סוכה, sukka, but nevertheless does the fact that
the, that it's a necessary, that somebody make a סוכה? sukka? Actually,
it's interesting, you don't even need a יהודי Yehudi to make a
סוכה. sukka. But anyway, and that it's mentioned in the תורה, Torah,
does that give it somehow some weight as at least a קיום
מצווה? kiyum mitzvah? But nevertheless, it is interesting. Most ראשונים Rishonim assume,
so what, if you take an oath not to do a קיום
מצווה, kiyum mitzvah, is that נשבע לבטל את המצווה? nishba l'vatel es
hamitzvah? Right, presumably not if you don't have to do it, but
anyway, but some ראשונים Rishonim basically assume it's לאו דווקא, lav davka,
it really means שלא לישב בסוכה. shelo leishev basukka. But it's good
that you picked that up. Okay, ושלא ליטול לולב ושלא להניח תפילין
זו היא שבועת שווא. v'shelo litol lulav v'shelo l'haniach tfillin zo hi
shvuat shav. So a שבועה shvua to negate a מצווה mitzvah serves
no purpose and therefore because it's not binding, and זו היא שבועת
שווא שחייבין על זדונה מכות, zo hi shvuat shav shechayavin al zdona
makot, if you willfully do this you get lashes, ועל שגגתה פטור,
v'al shigagata patur, but if you do it in error or in
negligence or whatever, then unaware, then you are exempt. Again, it's the
only thing that you bring a קרבן korban for is a שבועת
ביטוי shvuat bitui in the future, possibly in the past, but not
a שבועת שווא. shvuat shav. Now, what is missing from this is
this list is a שבועה, shvua, all of these cases you're basically
negating something, negating a thing that's obviously true, negating an obligation
to do
a מצווה, mitzvah, and
it calls that a שבועת שווא. shvuat shav. So there's elements of
שקר sheker if you think about it in the שבועת שווא. shvuat
shav. What about when there's no elements of שקר, sheker, when it's,
you know, but it's patently true or reinforcing an obligation? You know,
that is not clear from this משנה. Mishna. So just, just flagging
that. Now, let's finish the משנה.
Mishna. Like we had נדרי זירוזין nidrei ziruzin which were,
that's true, I mean that's a, you know, there, there could be
cases like that, that would be true, but that would be a
different consideration. Okay, שבועה שאוכל כיכר זו שבועה שלא אוכלנה. shvua she'ochel
kikar zo shvua shelo ochelena. Now, there's cases in the משנה Mishna
where we had an earlier case that you're redundant, שבועה שאוכל כיכר
זו שבועה שאוכלנה shvua she'ochel kikar zo shvua she'ochelena that the second
one isn't binding because it's, you know, it's
מושבע ועומד, mushba v'omed, right? אין שבועה חלה על שבועה. ein shvua
chala al shvua. And again, the sense is is that that would
not be a שבועת שווא. shvuat shav. Okay, let's say here you
took a, your second oath was to not eat it.
So therefore,
right, okay, now.
If that were the case maybe, but that's not the case. הראשונה
שבועת ביטוי, Harishona shvuat bitui, so the first one is a שבועת
ביטוי shvuat bitui that you're obligating yourself to do something in the
future, והשניה שבועת שווא, vehashnia shvuat shav, and the second one since
you're negating the obligation of a שבועת ביטוי, shvuat bitui, that's a
שבועת שווא. shvuat shav. אכלה, Achalah,
now אכלה, achalah, if you ate it, so עבר על שבועת שווא,
avar al shvuat shav, then you fulfilled your שבועת ביטוי, shvuat bitui,
you took a שבועה shvuah to eat it, but you transgressed your
second שבועה shvuah where you said you wouldn't eat it. לא אכלה,
Lo achalah, if you didn't eat it, so עבר על שבועת ביטוי,
avar al shvuat bitui, you transgressed your שבועת ביטוי shvuat bitui because
you said you would eat it. Now the sense of the משנה
mishna is you did not transgress your שבועת שווא shvuat shav because
you did exactly what your second שבועה shvuah said you would do,
which is did not eat it. But we'll see about that in
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, we'll deal with it in the גמרא. Gemara.
תוספות Tosafot by the way asks an interesting question for those who
were paying attention. Michael, I was waiting for you to ask this
question, which is: if he said before כיכר kikkar means the whole
thing, so then the second one really doesn't negate the first one.
The first one is you will eat this כיכר, kikkar, which you
would fulfill with a כזית, kazayit, and then you won't eat it
means you won't eat the whole thing. So you can fulfill both
שבועות, shvuot, both שבועות. shvuot. You eat a כזית kazayit and you
don't eat the whole thing. So anyway, תוספות Tosafot raises that question.
He doesn't really have a good answer. He says maybe if you
say I will eat it, it means I'll eat the whole thing.
If you say I won't eat it, then it maybe means I
won't even eat any part of it. Which you could sort of
hear, but anyway. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
So then it would mean that both of these take effect here.
Well, that's what it sounds like in the משנה, mishna, that they
both take effect and then you're sort of stuck. Either one you
do, you negate the other one. That's what the simple משנה mishna
sounds like. Okay, but we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara.
So when you say אכלה עבר על שבועת שווא, achala avar al
shvuat shav, isn't it שבועת שווא shvuat shav the moment you made
it?
That's exactly what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. It's going
to be... that's related to Charlie's question. We'll see that when we
get to it in the גמרא. Gemara. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, so
now we're going to deal with the case of something that is
patently false, it's a
שבועת שווא, shvuat shav, והוא שניכר לג' בני אדם. vehu shenikar legimel
bnei adam. It doesn't have to be transparently false to everybody, even
if it's only... even if only three people know that this pillar
is made out of stone and everybody else thinks it's gold because
it has a nice... well, what's the case?
Everybody... I take an oath that it is gold. It looks gold
because let's say it's got some nice, you know,
gold plated, or not even, because then you could argue that it
is gold.
It's painted in a gold color. So all you guys, you're so
ignorant, you all think it's gold. I know better. Three people know
that it's really stone, but most people saw it and most people
are uncertain. Okay, and I take an oath that it's made out
of gold. Now I gotta tell you, I would think that's a
שבועת שקר. shvuat sheker. I fooled all of you, most people are
uncertain, right?
I'm lying, I'm fooling all of you, I could be fooling a
thousand people with my שבועה, shvuah, they take my word for it
because they don't know any better, but because three people somewhere happen
to know that it's made out of stone, it's considered שבועת שווא
shvuat shav not a שבועת שקר? shvuat sheker? I really don't understand
this. You know, obviously it's based on the גמרא's Gemara assumption that
something known by three people is public and eventually people find out
about it, but like, you would think that it would have to
be counterbalanced. Like if, you know, if like, I don't know, it's
like if most people are under a different impression or most people...
like that we assume that because the facts are theoretically accessible and
available that makes it שווא shav and not שקר? sheker? I mean
that makes it, yeah, שווא shav and not שקר, sheker, that's pretty
funny. Okay, especially you know now living in the era of like
alternative facts and whatnot, you know the fact that certain facts are
discoverable doesn't really mean that necessarily people believe them and you say
false things with enough conviction, people believe you. You know, so really?
So it's not שקר, sheker, it's only שווא shav because people in
theory could get to the bottom of it? That seems just to
me very, very strange.
Especially depending on who these three people are, it could be...
you know, could be in Indonesia. Right, but you know, but even
if we grant that it means I don't know, three people in
the town, okay? But real...
I mean is the assumption that eventually people will realize that I
was lying? Really? A lot of lies are like that. I pull
the wool over your eyes for a period of time and then
eventually you realize I'm lying, you know? I don't know, it's very
strange. Okay,
נשבע, nishba, I mean what about if it's a case that it
was the three people was like even more private? Three people in
my family saw that I had eggs for breakfast and I take
an oath to you guys that I didn't have eggs for breakfast.
Is that... I assume that's שקר sheker not שווא, shav, right? Just
because... okay I don't know, maybe because my family keeps things private.
I don't know, three people at the diner saw that I had
eggs for breakfast, okay? And then I come to all of you
and I swear to you I didn't, what, that's a שווא? shav?
It's not a שבועת שקר shvuat sheker because three people know about
it? I don't agree. I have to assume that this is, that
the ג׳ בני אדם gimmel bnei adam is more contextual, you know,
but but I don't, I really don't. מעיד? me'id? מעיד me'id is
a case in which it really won't come to light very readily,
you know, or something of that nature. That's how I would like
to read it. All right. נשבע בדבר שאי אפשר לו, אם לא
ראיתי גמל פורח באויר. nishba bedavar she-ee efshar lo, im lo ra'iti
gamal porei'ach ba'avir. You swear about something that's impossible, like you say
if I did not see a camel flying in the air. When
camels fly. Or when horses fly. When donkeys fly. Now, שבועה, shvua,
now now what is why is this a שבועת שוא? shvuat shav?
What exactly is the שבועה shvua you took? So the משנה mishnah
says like this: שבועה שראיתי לא קאמר. shvua sherai'iti lo ka'amar. So
a שבועה shvua that I that I saw a camel, you didn't
say. מאי קאמר? mai ka'amar? Meaning that would be a שבועת שוא.
shvuat shav. If I got up and I said a שבועה shvua
that I saw a camel flying, okay? So that's patently false, and
that would be a simple example of a שבועת שוא. shvuat shav.
All right. But that wasn't the case. This is a great refrain
in the משנה mishnah was a שבועה shvua that I didn't see.
So what's the problem?
Unless again what you say what's absent in the משנה mishnah is
that if you say something that's patently true it also is a
שבועת שוא. shvuat shav. Again, that's not in the משנה. mishnah. But
then you could have said, if I if a guy took a
שבועה, shvua, a שבועה shvua that I didn't see a camel flying
in the air, okay, that's patently true. Maybe that's another example of
a שבועת שוא. shvuat shav. But again the משנה mishnah is not
dealing with that. The משנה mishnah is dealing with patently false. So
the גמרא's gemara got a problem. What's patently false about what he
said? So let's take a look. שבועה שראיתי לא קאמר. shvua sherai'iti
lo ka'amar. מאי אם לא ראיתי? mai im lo ra'iti? What does
it mean a שבועה shvua I didn't see? אביי אמר תני שבועה
שראיתי. Abaye amar tani shvua sherai'iti. Fine, yes, switch the גירסא, girsa,
it really means the guy took an oath that I did see
that I did see. So it's patently false. רבא אמר, Rava amar,
now רבא Rava says, ואומר יאסרו כל פירות שבעולם עלי בשבועה ve'omeir
ye'asru kol peirot sheba'olam alai bishvua is what it means, it says
that in another גמרא, gemara, all the fruit of the world will
be forbidden to me by an oath, אם לא ראיתי גמל פורח
באויר, im lo ra'iti gamal porei'ach ba'avir, if I did not see
a camel flying. Okay, now why is that a שבועת שוא? shvuat
shav? So you didn't see a camel flying, so all the fruit
is forbidden, so that's a שבועה. shvua. What's שבועת שוא shvuat shav
about that? So תוספות tosafot says it's really unclear in the גמרא,
gemara, so תוספות tosafot says it's a שבועת שוא, shvuat shav, forget
the condition, a camel flying, that really isn't the point. The point
is a person takes an oath that I won't eat all fruit
in the world forever. It's an oath that cannot be fulfilled. Okay?
It's like an oath that I'll never sleep, okay, where the גמרא
gemara says you give him lashes immediately for שבועת שוא shvuat shav
and he's allowed to sleep immediately. It's taking an oath about some
so the אי אפשר, ee efshar, impossible, doesn't mean the camel flying
is impossible. It means what's impossible... I know, so that's like bizarre.
The case of the camel flying is really completely trivial in the
משנה mishnah and incidental. The real point is a שבועה shvua to
do something that's to do something impossible, like to never eat any
fruit in the world, okay, I mean I guess it's possible. I'll
tell that to my kids. Yeah, exactly.
פירות peirot also in the משנה mishnah probably also means grains, so
therefore like also means I mean again, those are theoretically possible but
it's seen as as practically impossible. Okay, so first of all that's
a very bad read of a משנה. mishnah. The משנה mishnah emphasizes
a flying camel and according to this it's because you took a
שבועה shvua not to eat food, okay, or whatever. So anyway, that's
a very bad read. What I would still like to explore is
what if you to again swear about something that's patently true? Okay,
if the שבועה shvua that I did not see, why isn't that
a שבועת שוא shvuat shav because it's patently true as opposed to
something that's patently false. Anyway, that is seems to be from the
גמרא gemara discussion in the גמרא gemara not included in שבועת שוא.
shvuat shav. One other point: תוספות tosafot asks an interesting question. Would
I if I if I take an oath that I won't eat
all fruit, we say that's a שבועה shvua of something that's impossible
and it doesn't take effect and it's immediately a שבועת שוא. shvuat
shav. What if I focus I do it in a נדר neder
formulation? Let's say I said נדר neder all fruit in the world
is forbidden to me. So the effect of that is to make
to force me to do something impossible, okay, but the actual it's
not directly it's sort of like a נדר לבטל את המצוה, neder
levatel et hamitzvah, a נדר neder that I make סוכה sukkah forbidden
to me. Since the effect is undermines a מצוה mitzvah but it
doesn't directly go against my obligation, it takes effect. So when I
say I won't eat any fruit in the world and I take
a שבועה, shvua, so that directly contradicts, you know, my like what
I'm able to do and it relates to me and what I'm
requiring myself to do. So there's like a direct contradiction, so we
say it doesn't take effect, it's a שבועת שוא. shvuat shav. But
if I make all the fruit forbidden to me, okay, it's only
indirectly creating an impossible situation for me. It's not directly going against
my abilities. I'm not talking about my abilities. I'm talking about the
fruit. So תוספות tosafot actually has two opinions whether such a נדר
neder takes effect. Okay, it's very interesting. One opinion he says it
would for the reasons I just said, and the other we would
say no, a נדר neder whose whose effect is that it's unful
unable to be fulfilled, you know, humanly unable to be fulfilled, right,
is not a valid נדר. neder. And then he makes an interesting
point. Do I do anything wrong by taking a נדר? neder? Is
there a concept of נדר שוא? neder shav? Okay, let's say that
that's true, that such a נדר neder about all fruit is meaningless
and therefore it doesn't take effect. Have I done anything wrong by
saying that? What do you guys think? Is there a concept of
שבועת שוא? shevuat shav? או משבועת שוא?
o mishvuat shav? I would, I mean you'd assume so, but I
would think yes.
What? Okay, so first of all the תורה Torah never says don't,
you know, don't take a נדר שוא. neder shav. Right and also
but also more but it also gets to the very and the
reason I bring this out is it gets to the nature of
the שבועה. shevuah. The verse is לא תשא את שם ה' א-להיך
לשוא. Lo tisa et shem Hashem Elokecha lashav. The problem again that
going back to the beginning of the פרק perek that I've been
reiterating is that not just that a שבועה shevuah is about actions,
but a שבועה shevuah ultimately is about God's name. A שבועה shevuah
is about calling upon God to testify that what you are saying
is true, or you're going to sort of have to answer to
God, you you know if you do not live up to what
you are taking an oath about. So whether you explicitly say God's
name or not, it's always there in the background. Okay, so therefore
taking a שבועת שוא shevuat shav is taking God's name in vain.
Now that raises an interesting question. Let's say somebody doesn't mention God's
name and takes a שבועת שוא, shevuat shav, right, are they
violating לא תשא lo tisa because it's God's name is implicit? Okay,
that's an interesting question. But at the end of the day the
problem with a שבועת שוא shevuat shav is that it is an
invoking directly or by implication of God's name. Okay, whereas a נדר,
neder, you just did something foolish. You took a נדר neder that
didn't take effect. Okay, fine, whatever. Right, what did I do? Who
did I violate?
לא יחל דברו? Lo yechel devaro?
But it wasn't yet valid. It never took effect. No. Anyway, that's
תוספות Tosafot makes that point and I think that's very important to
A, to raise that question, does a נדר neder on all food
take effect or not? We could see arguments yes or no. And
B, if it doesn't, is there a concept of נדר שוא? neder
shav?
Okay, so you're saying there's no problem if it doesn't take effect
to make that kind of a נדר?
neder? It's possibly correct.
But I still don't understand, at some point you're going to have
to eat, in which case then your word will be...
No, it never took effect.
It never took effect because it can't happen. Right. So, in which
case then it's לא יחל דברו, Lo yechel devaro, you know what
I'm saying?
No, לא יחל דברו Lo yechel devaro is when it takes effect
and then you violate it. That would be the difference. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says here, I'll try to show you the law
in
תוספות... Tosafot...
No, he just says נדרי שוא לא מצינו. nidrei shav lo matzinu.
He doesn't give an explanation why not, but I think the explanation
is what I said, that it gets to the difference of whether
you're implicitly invoking God's name.
So what you're saying is even if a שבועה shevuah you didn't
invoke God's name then there's no problem?
So that's an interesting question. Yes, the assumption is yes, that the
איסור issur of שבועת שוא shevuat shav applies even without God's name
being invoked, but that would be because somehow it's implicit.
Like when you're saying I swear, you really mean I swear by
God even
if you don't say it? Exactly. That's the general question, does every
שבועה shevuah
implicitly mean as God is my witness? Is that what the mode
of a שבועה? shevuah?
And the other question to really think about here is, you know,
when we take a like a שבועה shevuah that oh I saw
like this this snake as big as whatever, you know? Like how
much do we contextualize this? He means I saw a really big
snake. You know what I mean? Isn't that like... why can't we
say that that's what he's trying...?
Okay, so we'll get to that in the גמרא. Gemara. Fine, calm
down. We'll get to it in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, alright. So
now let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. I'm going
to look up, I'm going to try to quote you the רמב"ם
Rambam about this issue. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי. Amar
leh Ravina l'Rav Ashi. So רבינא Ravina said to רב אשי, Rav
Ashi, ודילמא האי גברא ציפורא רבא חזי, u-dilma hai gavra tzipora raba
chazi, maybe how do you know this is a false oath, like
it's a שוא? shav? Let's say it's a simple case. A person
says he took an oath that he saw such a flying camel
and we say that's patently false and therefore it's a שבועת שוא.
shevuat shav. Okay, let's just go with that explanation. So he says,
how do you know it's patently false? Maybe the guy saw big
bird fly... Okay, Big Bird, right... ואסקי ליה שמא גמלא, v'aski leh
shema gamla, and he said that bird is so huge I'm going
to call that a camel. And then he said I saw camel
flying. He meant his pet bird who he's nicknamed camel. Okay, so
maybe... וכי קמשתבע אדעתא דידיה קמשתבע, v'chi kamishtava ada'ata dideh kamishtava, and
when he's taking an oath, he's taking oath in his own you
know based on his own meaning that he gives to those words.
Okay, so this gets to an important question, right, we've discussed all
along that a שבועה shevuah and a נדר neder have to be
פיו ולבו שוין. piv v'libo shavin. It goes by what you're thinking.
And what you're thinking sometimes תוספות Tosafot even discussed, you know, can
you ask the guy to clarify what he
meant? Okay, and and if they're not in sync between what you
said and what you meant it doesn't take effect. How much would
we go by its meaning, by what you're thinking, and we say...
and give it a meaning that is against that contradicts the normal
meaning that people would give to these words? That's different than contextualizing
and clarifying. That's giving it a bizarre meaning. Okay. So maybe maybe
we should say that's what you meant and therefore it wouldn't be
a שבועת שוא. shevuat shav. Okay, אדעתא דידיה קמשתבע. Ada'ata dideh kamishtava.
What?
That's where we're dealing with language. Right. Somebody's making his own private
language.
Right, you know, that's, you know, that's kind of like outside the
frame. Right, but this is at least a little bit like if
you explain to them, Oh no, my pet bird... parakeet's name is
Camel, so then he didn't really violate the rules of the language,
right? It's just that everybody, but nevertheless, yes, that's exactly the question.
וכי תימא בתר פומי אזלינן ולא אזלינן בתר דעתיה V'chi teima batar
pumi azlinan v'lo azlinan batar da'teih and if you say no, he's
not allowed to say those things, we go by his lips and
not by his mind. We go by what he said, not by
what he was thinking. And yes, can his thinking
sometimes contextualize and clarify? Maybe. But it can't give a meaning that
is clearly against the standard meaning that any normal meaning people would
give this. So that would be a reasonable thing to say.
So now the גמרא's Gemara going to get into that question. Can
you go by somebody's intent even in ways that it contradicts what
they say when it comes to
their שבועה? shevuah? והתניא, V'hatanya, but we taught in the ברייתא, braita,
כשמשביעין אותו אומרים לו, kshe'mashbi'in oto omrim lo, when you this is
when they give somebody an oath in בית דין Beit Din and
they say to the
person, Michael, take an oath that you say you don't owe Charlie
$100. Take an oath that you don't owe Charlie $100.
And we say, Michael, we don't want any tricks. We don't want
you to assign your own personal meaning to those words. So when
we're making you take this oath, it's not what you think these
words mean, it's what we say these words mean. כשמשביעין אותו אומרים
לו הוי יודע שלא על דעתך אנו משביעים אותך, kshe'mashbi'in oto omrim
lo hevei yodea shelo al datcha anu mashbi'im otcha, not what you
want to claim those words are going to mean when they come
out of your mouth, אלא על דעתנו ela al dateinu on our
דעת da'at and על דעת בית דין v'al da'at Beit Din and
the דעת da'at of בית דין, Beit Din, well I mean they
are בית דין, Beit Din, but whatever, we'll worry about that. על
דעת המקום ועל דעת בית דין al da'at Hamakom v'al da'at Beit
Din is another version of it. Exactly. Well that's where we get
it from. So מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why is it that we
do that? לאו משום דאמרינן דילמא lav mishum d'amrinan dilma because we
must be afraid that he's giving a private meaning to those words.
דילמא איסקונדרי יהיב ליה, dilma iskundrei yahiv leh, maybe Michael gave Charlie
100 little slips of paper. I think that's what
רש״י Rashi says, איסקונדרי, iskundrei, little like wood chips. He dumped off
a bag of paperclips by Charlie before the court case. ואסיק להו
זוזי v'asik lehu zuzei and he said, "Oh yeah, I have a
nickname for those paperclips, I call each paperclip a dollar." So then
when I come to court, I'm going to swear that I gave
Charlie
$100. והכי משתבע דעתי דידי קא משתבע. v'hachi mishtava da'atei didei ka
mishtava. We're afraid of that. So the fact that we're afraid of
that and we have to preempt it by saying it's going to
be the meaning we give it, shows that if we don't preempt
it, you're entitled to give it your own private meaning. Is that
not evidence? The fact that we need to do this, that otherwise
you are entitled to give it your own private meaning? One minute
Charlie. לא התם משום קניא דרבא. lo hatam mishum kanya d'Rava. No.
There it's possible that it's not a private meaning but it's a
trick meaning. What's the trick
meaning? It was the story with רבא. Rava. So the case came
before רבא, Rava, we'll do it again with Michael and Charlie. Michael
owed Charlie $100, which he was denying. So what Michael did was
he took his walking stick and he carved out a hole in
it and he put $100 in it, screwed the top back on
and then he got up to make a שבועה shevuah and he
said to Charlie, "Here Charlie, hold my stick for me for a
minute," and then he took an oath that he gave Charlie $100.
So there actually he's not giving a private meaning to the words,
he actually did give Charlie $100 but in circumstances which are clearly
different than anything we obviously are referring to. So you would have
to say do it on our דעת, da'at, not because you could
give a private meaning to the words, you'll make the words mean
something else, but that the context might be such like אנכי עשו
בכורך, Anochi Esav bechorecha, you'll do something, whatever the context will be
such that it's not at all what we're talking about. So that's
why you have to do it. All of this of course makes
me think about Bill
Clinton, right? What does
"is" mean, what is the meaning of "is"?
Or Mary McCarthy talking about the same about Lillian Hellman, everything she
writes is a lie, including the words "and" and "the".
So, okay. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear.
וכן מצינו כשנשביע משה את ישראל. v'chein matzinu kshe'hishbia Moshe et Yisrael.
We have found that when משה Moshe made בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
take an oath right there at ערבות מואב, Arvot Moav, לא אתכם
לבדכם, lo itchem levadchem, not you alone am I taking this oath,
but everybody who's not here. אמר להן, amar lahen, he said, דעו
שלא על דעתכם אני משביע אתכם, de'u shelo al datchtem ani mashbia
etchem, when I make you take this oath to fulfill the תורה,
Torah, it's not just what you want to think it means, אלא
על דעת המקום ועל דעתי, ela al da'at Hamakom v'al da'ati, that's
like דעת המקום da'at Hamakom דעת השם, da'at Hashem, what God says
it means and what I say it means. So don't make any
tricks that you're trying to give different meanings to these words. Now
I just want to pause for a moment. תוספות Tosafot asks a
great question. תוספות Tosafot says what could a שבועה shevuah do? You're
already obligated, so if you don't feel bound by מצוות, mitzvot, why
are you going to feel bound by your שבועה? shevuah? If you
look at תוספות כשנשביע משה את ישראל, Tosafot kshe'hishbia Moshe et Yisrael,
תוספות Tosafot says קצת קשה מאי מהניא להו השבועה דמאחר שהיו יראים
שיעבדו עבודת כוכבים כל שכן דלא לירפו פן יעברו השבועה. ktzat kashe
mai mahanya lehu hashevuah d'me'acher she'hayu yere'im she'ya'avdu avodat kochavim kol sheken
d'lo lirpu pan ya'avru hashevuah. I don't understand, says תוספות, Tosafot, if
somebody's not going to fulfill the מצוות mitzvot that God said, what's
going to make them fulfill it more because they took an oath?
Because they want to keep their word. Right.
So obviously you could... The psychological answer is that it's very different
when it's something imposed on you by others and if you actually
obligate yourself, like your integrity is on the line, right? It's not
just are you living up to some obligation somebody put to you.
You are standing by your word, it gets to like a core
of who you are and your integrity is on the line, it
obviously's not just the עונש onesh of a שבועה. shvua. Actually, what's
his name,
the פחד יצחק, Pachad Yitzchak, רב יצחק הוטנר Rav Yitzchak Hutner makes
this point about מעמד הר סיני Ma'amad Har Sinai itself. And he
says Moshe goes to בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael and says, okay, God's
going to give you these מצוות, mitzvot, are you going to give
them? And they say yes, right? And like the מדרש Midrash is
even like, you know, God hangs them out then over them, will
you accept this? And they say yes. He says why do they
have to say yes? What does that do for them? Like that's
even before any מצוות mitzvot were given. So there would have been
no עבירה, aveira, and if they obligated themselves, there would not even
have been an עבירה aveira involved in not living up to their
self-obligation, because they had not yet, you know, because they weren't yet
living in a world of מצוות, mitzvot, okay? So he says so
what is the idea? He actually makes a bigger philosophical point, like
this is a general question, which is like, you know, do all
ethics only proceed from God or, you know, is there a sense
of independent ethics? And his point really is there has to be
some sense of independent ethics because if it was all just proceeding
from
God, well, then like why does it make sense to obligate myself
to accept the מצוות mitzvot from God if everything just comes from
God? It's the same as God commanding it. Anyway, so he basically
sort of uses that as an interesting evidence to the power of
a sense of an ethical obligation even independent of the divine command
and how that, you know, becomes the framework for binding yourself to
what God had said. So that's actually quite fascinating in terms of
thinking about the power of the שבועה shvua and independent, you know,
your own commitment or promise or word independent of any מצווה mitzvah
or עבירה aveira or divine ethical context. Okay, so anyway it says
דעו שלא על דעתכם אני משביע אתכם אלא על דעת המקום ועל
דעתי. de'u she-lo al da'at-chem ani mashbi'a et-chem ela al da'at ha-makom
ve'al da'ati. ואמאי? ve'amai? Now, why does he have to say that?
The only reason he would have to say that is he's afraid
that people will give private meanings to the words. לימא להו leima
lehu he could just say קימו מה דאמר אלוה, kimu ma de-amar
Eloha,
fulfill everything God has said. And he doesn't have to say what
other, what other meaning could they give unless they're giving private meaning
to the words? But without private meaning, why does he have to
say, oh, it's based on what I say it means? Okay, לא
משום דקמסקי אדעתייהו עבודת כוכבים. lo mishum de-kamaski ada'atayhu avodat kochavim.
Isn't it because that they will say אלוה Eloha means, you know,
means the idolatrous gods? Okay, and they'll give that private meaning to
the word. So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no, yes, it
is that's the problem, but it says not because it's a private
meaning, that actually that is a meaning of the word אלוה. Eloha.
And where do you, the meaning of the word God is lowercase
g god not capital G God. משום דעבודת כוכבים נמי איקרי אלוה
דכתיב אלוהי כסף ואלוהי זהב. mishum de-avodat kochavim nami ikri Eloha de-chtiv
elohei chesef ve'elohei zahav. Okay, I know, there's so many examples, אלוהים
אחרים Elohim acherim and so on, maybe it means that, I don't,
anyway. So the point is the problem there's not a private meaning
of
the word. Moshe would say something and they would say, oh you're
referring to an idolatrous god, you're not referring to our God. That's
how they would get out of it, okay? Which is not a
private meaning. Okay, תוספות Tosafot says why didn't they just use the
name י-ה-ו-ה? Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei? תוספות Tosafot raises the possibility that maybe even that
name could be assigned to some for, might be, you know, a
name used by some other god, which is fascinating. Anyway, I know,
I know, you can look at תוספות. Tosafot. ולימא להו קימו תורה.
ve-leima lehu kimu Torah. So fine, forget God. Let's say they say
accept the תורה. Torah. Okay, so what would he be afraid of
unless it would be some private meaning? Let's say no, תורה Torah
is ambiguous even in terms of its accepted meaning. חדא תורה, chada
Torah, it means one תורה, Torah, so they wouldn't have to do
שבעל פה. she-ba'al peh. ולימא קימו שתי תורות, ve-leima kimu shtei torot,
fulfill both תורות. Torot. תורת חטאת, Torat chatat, תורת אשם, Torat asham,
there's a lot of things that are called תורה. Torah. Again, not
a private meaning, just not what you were, not the meaning you
were thinking. Okay, כל התורה כולה, kol ha-Torah kula, let's say they
say keep the entire תורה. Torah. So what other meaning could they
give unless a private one? No, here's a good meaning that they
could give that would be a recognized meaning. עבודת כוכבים, avodat kochavim,
it just means don't do עבודה זרה. avoda zara. You know, keep
the whole תורה Torah means keep the essence of the
תורה. Torah. דאמר מר חמור עבודת כוכבים שכל הכופר בה כמודה בכל
התורה כולה, da'amar mar chamur avodat kochavim she-kol ha-kofer bah ke-modeh be-chol
ha-Torah kula, that if you reject עבודה זרה avoda zara it's like
you fulfill the whole תורה. Torah. So that's an acceptable meaning of
what you said, not a private meaning. ולימא ve-leima why not say
to them להו קימו מצוה, lehu kimu mitzva, fulfill the מצוה? mitzva?
It's a funny הוה אמינא hava amina just to get to the
next answer. חדא מצוה, chada mitzva, fine, one מצוה, mitzva, that I
can do. קימו מצוות, kimu mitzvot, do the מצוות. mitzvot. תרתי, tarti,
fine, I'll do two. Okay, קימו כל המצוות כולן, kimu kol ha-mitzvot
kulan, fulfill all the מצוות. mitzvot. All right, ציצית, tzitzit, fine, I'll
adopt ציצית, tzitzit, and that's not a private meaning, that's an acceptable
interpretation of the words fulfill all the מצוות. mitzvot. Why? דאמר מר
שקולה מצות ציצית כנגד כל המצוות כולן. da'amar mar shkula mitzvat tzitzit
ke-neged kol ha-mitzvot kulan. מצוה, mitzvah, ציצית, tzitzit, you know, reminds you
of all the מצוות. mitzvot. רש"י Rashi does a גימטריה gematria where
it gets close to תרי"ג taryag plus the strings plus
the
knots, fine. So the גמרא Gemara says וליתמיך, v'litaymeich, fine, you got
me there. If it weren't for private meanings, maybe they couldn't, but
that doesn't prove the concern is private meanings. How do I know
that doesn't prove it, that the concern is a private meaning? וליתמיך
v'litaymeich according to you, okay, לימא להו על דעתי ועל דעת המקום
למה לי. leima lehu al da'ati v'al da'as hamakom lama li. So
why does he say on God's intent? Why doesn't he just say
on my meaning? So clearly there's more going on here than the
possibility of excluding private meanings. Okay, אלא, ella, let's do כי היכי
דלא תהוי הפרה לשבועתייהו. ki heichi d'lo tehei hafara l'shvuasaihu. When you
say על דעתי ועל דעת המקום, al da'ati v'al da'as hamakom, that
really has nothing to do with excluding private meanings. This proves nothing
about the private meanings. It means, well, the גמרא's Gemara's claim is
that we're not. The argument was that we were and they were
trying to prove it from the need to say על דעתי. al
da'ati. And the answer is no, I'm going to continue to claim
that we're not concerned for private meanings, okay, and that's why I'm
not concerned that your pet parrot is called Camel. We're not concerned
for private meanings, and the reason משה Moshe did this and said
על דעת המקום ועל דעת הקהל al da'as hamakom v'al da'as hakahal
was so that they couldn't go to some חכם chacham and get
a התרה. hatara. By saying על דעתי al da'ati doesn't just mean
on the meaning I give the words, but it also means that
you are bound—the התרה hatara process works because you said it wasn't
my intention in these circumstances to have taken the שבועה. shvua. But
what I'm saying is, it's not just your intention, buddy, it's my
intention as well. So even if we completely agree what the words
mean, right, the bindingness of the שבועה shvua is not just bound
on your intent to fulfill it, where then you could go to
a התרת נדרים hataras nedarim and say in these circumstances I wouldn't
have done it, it's bound to the degree that I want you
to fulfill it, and I want you to fulfill it regardless of
circumstances and so on. Okay, so that's what it does. It operates
in a very different way, not about the meaning but about the
bindingness. And therefore, bottom line is, we're not concerned about private meanings
of words. Now תוספות Tosafos makes an interesting point because this phrase,
right, like as we know that we do on יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, על דעת המקום ועל דעת הקהל, al da'as hamakom v'al da'as
hakahal, was actually a classic phrase that they did when they would
make, you know, a classic way in the Middle Ages that they
would make rules for the community and then get people to live
by them, was to basically impose a שבועה shvua on the whole
community or a חרם, cherem, and they would say על דעת המקום
ועל דעת הקהל al da'as hamakom v'al da'as hakahal and so on.
But sometimes they would have a need to revoke it or to
make a waiver. So take a look at
תוספות. Tosafos. כי היכי דלא תהוי הפרה לשבועתייהו. ki heichi d'lo tehei
hafara l'shvuasaihu. הדר מינה נדר שהוא על דעת רבים אין לו הפרה.
hadar minei neder shehu al da'as rabim ein lo hafara. Okay, now
it sounds like על דעת רבים, al da'as rabim, you know, on
our דעת, da'as, on God's דעת, da'as, it sounds like you can't
annul
it. דהיינו אינו מזה מכאן דהיינו שניים לחודייהו. dehaini einu mazei mikan
dehaini shnayim l'chudayhu. First of all, just because you have משה Moshe
and God, it doesn't mean the definition of רבים rabim is two.
Okay, that's not just why we're saying משה Moshe and God. דלמא
דעת קודשא בריך הוא שאני. dilma da'as kudsha berich hu shani. Yeah,
God counts for more than just one vote. Okay, so anyway, so
we don't know how many people you need to make something constitute
a דעת רבים. da'as rabim. Okay. ואם תאמר, V'im tomar, באותן חרמות
שאנו גוזרים על דעת הקדוש ברוך הוא ועל דעת הקהל, b'osan charamos
she'anu gozrim al da'as hakadosh baruch hu v'al da'as hakahal, we say
חרם, cherem, like think of חרם רבינו גרשום, Cherem Rabbeinu Gershom, right?
On the דעת da'as of God and on the דעת da'as of
the community, the community is the דעת רבים, da'as rabim, okay, it's
not—right, so it's על דעת רבים, al da'as rabim, so you can't
annul it. Okay. So now תוספות Tosafos says היכי יש להן היתר?
heichi yesh lahen heter? How do we—because sometimes we actually do waive
it, we revoke it after a period of time or whatever we
do. How do we do that? It's supposed to be maybe for
a particular person under extenuating circumstances, right? So, you know, there's interesting
cases, one example comes to mind, for example, that you don't know—you
wouldn't know—like חרם רבינו גרשום. Cherem Rabbeinu Gershom. They made a—the גאונים
Geonim made a תקנה, takana, people would get—the people would, you know,
horrors of horrors, sometimes get married for love against the will of
the parents of the bride and the groom. Or sometimes somebody would
marry a girl, like an unsuspecting young woman, and then, you know,
and then extort the parents for like a lot of money to
divorce her and whatever. So they made a תקנה takana that nobody
is allowed to do קידושין, kidushin, not the נישואין, nisuin, not the
חופה, chuppah, קידושין kidushin without ten people there and the rabbi there
or whatever it was, the parents there and so on. Okay, but
let's say you had, I don't know, some extenuating circumstance, somebody was
in jail, right, you couldn't get ten people present or whatever, right?
How could—so they would make a waiver. But how can you make
a waiver? It's על דעת רבים, al da'as rabim, על דעת הקהל,
al da'as hakahal, and אין לו התרה. ein lo hatara. So תוספות
Tosafos says היכי יש להן היתר? heichi yesh lahen heter? דאפילו על
דעת הקהל גרידא—forget d'afilu al da'as hakahal gareda even God in this
equation—even if you just said על דעת הקהל, al da'as hakahal, הוי
על דעת רבים. havei al da'as rabim. That would be על דעת
רבים. al da'as rabim. ועוד היכי משתרי בלא חרטה? V'od heichi mishtarei
b'lo charata? And anyway, how do we waive it if there's no
process of חרטה? charata? Okay, it's just we, the קהל, kahal, are
deciding that this case deserves a waiver. But if we're imposing it
on you, okay, but maybe not a מצווה mitzvah case, if we're
imposing it on you, don't you need to go through a process
of asking a חכם chacham and... So it says ויש לומר *veyeish
lomar* דעת הקהל כך הוא *da'as hakahal kach hu*, this is exactly
what the דעת הקהל *da'as hakahal* is. It prevents you on your
own from going and doing a התרה *hatara* and it gives us
the קהל *kahal* or the rabbis who are the representatives of the
קהל *kahal* the complete discretion. It's our דעת *da'as* to determine whether
to be מוותר *mevater* in this case. Right. כך הוא שיתירו כשירצו
ואפילו בלא חרטה *kach hu sheyatiru keshayirtzu va'afilu belo charata*. Okay, so
that's basically how it works. But it means even the קהל *kahal*
doesn't have to do חרטה *charata*. It's not like the בית דין
beis din *beis din* representing the קהל *kahal* has to go to
another בית דין beis din, *beis din* and say, how had we
known in this case we wouldn't have imposed it on Michael who's
in jail and needs a special... no, you don't need to go
through the process at all. It's our דעת *da'as* and our דעת
*da'as* basically means, a, you don't get to decide to go to
a חכם *chacham*, and b, we have total discretion whether to waive
it or not. So that's very interesting in terms of the mechanism.
So now he says, why are we mentioning God? Okay, since ultimately
it's our דעת *da'as* that matters here. So he says ומה שמזכירין
דעת הקדוש ברוך הוא *umah shemazkirin da'as hakadosh baruch hu*, we say
על דעת המקום *al da'as hamakom*, we add God to the equation.
תקנו הגאונים לחומרא בעלמא *tiknu hageonim lechumra be'alma*. Yeah, that's just because
it makes it sound weightier. שלא דמי למה שהשביע משה שהקדוש ברוך
הוא צוה להשביע *shelo dami lema shehishbia moshe shehakadosh baruch hu tzivah
lehashbia*. When Moshe called God, invoked God, that was because God told
him to impose it. Okay, אבל חרמות שנגזרו הכל תלוי בדעת הקהל
לחוד *aval charamos shenigzaru hakol taluy beda'as hakahal lachud*. We say God,
but it's really all about us, what we decide. Okay.
So yeah, I know, it's very human.
Exactly. Okay, so I thought that was fascinating in terms of its
practical, okay, and historical. וההוא דאמר *ve'hahu de'amar*, okay, so the גמרא
Gemara *gemara* says חזיתיה חיויא דהוי כי נרשבא דאולפי *chazisei chivya dehavay
ke'narshava de'ulfei*. I haven't seen a snake like the size of a
beam of an olive press. ולא *velo*? Is that not possible? וההוא
דהוה בשני שבור מלכא *ve'hahu dehavay bishnei shavor malka*? Wasn't there a
snake at the time of Shavor Malka? הוה חד דאכיל תליסר אורוותא
תבנא *havay chad de'achil telaisar urvasa tivna*. One snake actually swallowed up
twelve like troughs of grain... of of whatever of what's תבן *teven*...
straw. Okay.
snakes are big, you know, you hear about this in India, like
people getting swallowed by these big snakes.
Right, exactly. So אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel, בטרוף *amar shmuel betaruf*. It's
referring to a snake, it doesn't just mean it's as big as
the beam, it means it's like notched, like it's got spots or
stripes on it like this beam does. That's how beams would have
notches in them. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says כולהו נמי מיטרף
טריפי *kulehu nami mitraf treifei*? All snakes have stripes on them or
spots? בשיגבו טרוף *beshigbo taruf*. No, the back of it is striped
and that apparently, I don't know, doesn't happen with snakes. איך ווייס
נישט *ich veis nisht*. All right, anyway. שבועה shevuah. שאוכל ככר זו
שבועה shevuah שלא אוכלנה *shvuah she'ochal kikar zo shvuah she'lo ochelenah*. So
now the משנה Mishnah. *mishnah* says if you take a שבועה shevuah.
*shvuah* to eat and then not eat, it sounds like you have
to make a choice. You're going to violate one of them. Are
you going to eat it? Then you've violated the 'not eat'. Are
you going to not eat? You've violated the 'eat'. But it sounds
like, right, it's one or the other. But the גמרא Gemara. *gemara*
has a problem, which is Michael's problem, which is as soon as
you took the second שבועה shevuah *shvuah* that you won't eat it,
that already was a שבועת שוא shevuat shav, *shvuas shav*, that was
never a binding... okay, so if you don't eat it, right, you
don't not violate that שבועה shevuah *shvuah*. That שבועה shevuah *shvuah* was
a שבועת שוא Shevuat shav, *shvuas shav* the minute it left your
lips. Okay, which is what the גמרא Gemara. *gemara* says. התם משום
שבועת ביטוי Shevuat bituy. מחייב *hasam mishum shvuas bituy mechayev*. So I
don't get it, says the גמרא *gemara*, if you went ahead and
you didn't eat it, which was your second שבועה shevuah *shvuah*, so
you only transgressed your first one? משום שבועת שוא shevuat shav לא
מחייב *mishum shvuas shav lo mechayev*? You didn't transgress your... you know,
the שבועת שוא shevuat shav. *shvuas shav*? הרי יצאה שבועה shevuah לשוא
*harei yatza shvuah leshav* when you said it was לשוא *leshav* because
it was לבטל את המצוה *levatel es hamitzvah*. So אמר רבי ירמיה
תני אף על שבועת ביטוי shevuat bituy, *amar rabbi yirmiyah tani af
al shvuas bituy*. Fine, you're right. You always violate שבועת שוא *shvuas
shav*. And if you went ahead and you fulfilled the שבועת שוא
*shvuas shav*, you still violated the שבועת שוא *shvuas shav* and you
also violated the שבועת ביטוי shevuat bituy. *shvuas bituy*. But not like
the רישא *reisha*. It's not like you have a choice. Okay, you
always did the שבועת שוא *shvuas shav* and we'll see whether you're
going to violate the שבועת ביטוי shvuat bitui, *shvuas bituy*. Okay, so
now we wrap up, so I thought this whole דף *daf* would
go quickly, we're having too much fun. Okay, but before we read
this, let me just see if I can quickly quote for you
the רמב"ם Rambam *rambam* here
about this issue. Hold on, hold on, what we were talking about.
Here, here is what רמב"ם Rambam *rambam* says: שבועת שוא נחלקה לארבעה
מחלקות *shvuas shav nechelka le'arbaa
machalakos*. Doesn't mean divisions, not debate. האחת שנשבע על דבר ידוע שאין
כן *ha'achas shenishba al davar yadua she'ein kein*, okay. השנייה שנשבע על
דבר ידוע שאין בו ספק לאדם שהוא כן *hashniya shenishba al davar
yadua she'ein bo safek le'adam shehu kein*. Okay, so there you go.
So that's reaffirming something that is obvious. So that wasn't in our
משנה Mishnah. *mishnah*, but I mentioned it to you. Okay. השלישית שנשבע
לבטל את המצוה *hashlishis shenishba levatel es hamitzvah*. הרביעית שנשבע על דבר
שאין לו כוח בה לעשותו *harevi'is shenishba al davar she'ein lo koach
bah la'asoso*. Okay,
like he takes an oath that he won't sleep or שלא יטעם
*shelo yit'am*, etc. So interesting what is absent from רמב"ם Rambam *rambam*
is... so you do have something that's patently true, but you don't
have a redundant שבועה shvuah. *shvuah*, right? If you take a שבועה
shvuah, *shvuah* שאוכלנה שאוכלנה *she'ochelenah she'ochelenah* or שבועה shvuah, *shvuah* not to
eat חזיר *chazir* or whatever, even though אין שבועה shvuah חלה על
שבועה *ein shvuah chala al shvuah*, that is not a שבועת שוא
*shvuas shav*, which is interesting. Okay, now the question about whether שם
השם *shem hashem* is implicated in this... I'm trying to remember that
is... I should have checked this up,
but let me just quickly see,
oh here we go. Rambam says like this: אחד הנשבע או שהשביעו
אחר בשם המיוחד או באחד מן הכינויים, o be'echad min hakinuyim, like
being נשבע nishba by whoever's name is חנון Chanun or by whoever's
name is רחום Rachum or by whoever's name is ארך אפים Erech
Apayim וכיוצא בהן, vechayotzei vahen, בכל אלו הרי זו שבועה גמורה. bechol
elu harey zu shevuah gemurah.
If you use God's name, it's a full שבועה. Okay. וכן אלה
ארור vechen alah arur
etc. Okay, if you use God's name, okay, da da da. וכן
אומר שבועה בהשם ומי ששמעו שלא אוכל vechen omer shevuah baHashem umi
sheshema'o shelo ochal etc. Fine. אלה או ארור או שבועה ולא הזכיר
שם, Alah o arur o shevuah velo hizkir shem, let's say you
took a שבועה without mentioning God's name, okay, הרי זה אסור בדבר
שנשבע עליו, harey ze asur badavar shenishba alav, אבל אינו לוקה ולא
מביא קרבן אם עבר על שבועתו עד שיהיה בה שם מן השמות
או כינוי
מן הכינויים. aval eino loke velo mevi korban im avar al shevuato
ad sheyiheye bah shem min hashemot o kinuy min hakinuyim.
The Rambam says all of the things we've been discussing, okay, with
the קרבן korban or מלקות malkus etc., all of that is only
when God's name is explicit. So there's an interesting question: does Rambam
mean to say without God's name it's only rabbinic? Or does he
mean to say it's biblical but because it lacks that element of
violating God's name or taking God's name in vain, it's not weighty
enough, it's like a חצי שיעור. chatzi shi'ur. You know, it's not
weighty enough to bring a קרבן korban or to get מלקות? malkus?
Maybe, but you get lashes for לא יחל דברו lo yachel devaro
anyway, so it's not, right? So that really shows about how central
the idea of God's name is to שבועה.
A very large steak with a flat back and spots. שקויח. shkayach.
Anaconda. Okay,
let's take a look. Wrapping this up. שבועת ביטוי. shvuat bitui Okay,
now the שבועת ביטוי, which is again the simple example is future
oriented, נוהגת באנשים ובנשים, noheget beanshim uvenashim, you would bring a קרבן
בשוגג, korban beshogeg, נוהגת באנשים ובנשים noheget beanshim uvenashim whether men or
women, בקרובים וברחוקים, bikrovim uverechokim, relatives or not relatives. Now what's a
relative? Why? So that's really coming to contrast it to the idea
of the next פרק perek or the lead-in to the next פרק,
perek, which is a שבועת העדות. shevuat ha'edut. So if I ask
somebody who's a relative, a woman to testify, it's not a binding
שבועת העדות, shevuat ha'edut, she's not an acceptable
witness.
If she does then swear falsely,
yeah, it might be שבועת שוא, but it's certainly not שבועת העדות.
shevuat ha'edut. If I have a, if I ask a relative a
שבועה to testify, it's also not binding because a relative can't testify
for me. Okay, so that's why we're contrasting it exactly. But relative
by itself is a little meaningless in this context. Rashi says an
example of relative is I take a שבועה that I'll give my
brother 10 dollars, or I take a שבועה that I'll give a
stranger 10 dollars, that's קרובים ורחוקים. krovim urechokim. Okay. בכשרים ובפסולים, Biksherim
uvisulim, whether the person taking the שבועה is
כשר kasher to give testimony or even if he's like a גנב
ganav or somebody who's פסול pasul to give testimony. Okay. בפני בית
דין ושלא בפני בית דין, Bifney beit din ushelo bifney beit din,
whether it took place in the presence of the court or not.
Right again, all of this might be relevant for a שבועת העדות,
shevuat ha'edut, but not for a normal שבועת ביטוי. מפי עצמו, Mipi
atzmo, only those you did it yourself, not imposed by, implicitly not
imposed by others, although we'll get to the case in the גמרא
about imposed by others. וחייבין על זדונה מלקות ועל שגגתה קרבן עולה
ויורד. Vechayavin al zedonah malkus ve'al shegagatah korban oleh veyored. Again, what
we said before: if you willingly violated it, you get lashes; if
you unintentionally violate it, you bring the קרבן korban of variable cost.
שבועת שוא, now a שבועת שוא נוהגת באנשים ובנשים, noheget beanshim uvenashim,
men, women, בקרובים וברחוקים, bikrovim uverechokim, relatives and not relatives, בכשרים ובפסולים,
biksherim uvisulim,
whether
you're כשר kasher to testify or not, בפני בית דין ושלא בפני
בית דין,
bifney beit din ushelo bifney
beit din, in presence of בית דין Beit Din. and not in
presence of בית דין, Beit Din ומפי עצמו, umipi atzmo, and only
again if you said it yourself. Now, וחייבין על זדונה מלקות ועל
שגגתה פטור. vechayavin al zedonah malkus ve'al shegagatah patur. And you get
מלקות malkus for doing it willfully, but unintentionally there's no קרבן. korban.
It's a שבועת שוא. Interesting he didn't mention שבועת שקר, shevuat sheker,
which he could have sort of said the same thing. אחת זו
ואחת זו, Achat zu ve'achat zu, now we've discussed by you said
it by yourself. How about if it was imposed on you by
others? Okay, meaning somebody said משביע אני עליך, masbi'a ani alecha, I
impose a שבועה on you, and you said אמן. amen. You said
yes. Okay, now you could say if the whole problem is לא
תשא את שם השם אלהיך לשוא lo tisa et shem Hashem elokecha
lashav or לא תשבעו בשמי לשקר, lo tishav'u bishmi lashaker,
so if you didn't actually say it yourself, maybe you're not violating.
So it says, אחת זו ואחת זו המושבע מפי אחרים חייב. achat
zu ve'achat zu hamushba mipi acherim chayav. You are חייב, chayav, even
though a minute ago we just said it has to be מפי
עצמו, mipi atzmo, by yourself. So which is it? Does it have
to be you say it yourself or even by others? So the
גמרא's going to deal with the different implications of the beginning and
the end of the משנה. Mishnah, Now, somebody says לא אכלתי היום
ולא הנחתי תפילין, lo achalti hayom velo hinachti tefillin,
I didn't eat today, I didn't put on תפילין, tefillin, משביע אני
עליך, masbi'a ani alecha, and here's an example of somebody making you
swear,
I impose an oath on you about
that, ואמר אמן, ve'amar amen, yes, I accept that, חייב. chayav. Okay,
so מושבע מפי אחרים mushba mipi acherim is חייב. chayav. So why
did we say initially that you have to be מפי עצמו? mipi
atzmo? So let's take a look at the גמרא. אמר שמואל, Shmuel,
says שמואל, Shmuel כל העונה אמן אחר שבועה כמוציא שבועה מפיו דמי.
kol ha'oneh amen achar shevuah kemotzi shevuah mipiv dami.
Here's he's going to answer it. Yes, you do have to say
it yourself. But the words אמן, Amen, אמן, Amen, since words came
out of your mouth, wrapped up into that word אמן, Amen, if
we were to take a monitor and unpack the word אמן, Amen,
packed up into that word is everything the other guy said. Okay,
so therefore it's like you yourself said the שבועה. כמוציא שבועה מפיו
דמי, kemotzi shvuah mipiv dami, דכתיב, dechtiv, ואמרה האשה אמן אמן, veamra
haishah Amen Amen,
which is exactly responding to an oath imposed by somebody else.
It's like he said it himself. אמר רב פפא משמיה דרבא, Amar
Rav Pappa mishmei deRava, מסייעא ליה ברייתא נמי דיקא, mesayeya lei baraita
nami dika, that's also inferred from our Mishnah-Baraita. דתני, detani, שבועת העדות,
shvuat haedut, the Mishnah coming up in the tomorrow, נוהגת באנשים ולא
בנשים, noheget beanshim velo benashim, ברחוקים ולא בקרובים, berachokim velo bekrovim, in
exact contrast to ours. Only men, not women. Only non-relatives, not relatives.
בכשרים ולא בפסולים, bechsherim velo bifsulim, only people that are כשר kasher
to testify. ואינה נוהגת אלא למי שראוי להעיד, veina noheget ela lemi
sheraui lehaid, only somebody that's fit to testify. ובפני בית דין, ubifnei
Beit Din, and in the presence of the court. Now what about
not in the presence of the court? ושלא בפני בית דין מפי
עצמו. veshelo bifnei Beit Din mipi atzmo. Okay, now if
it's בפני בית דין ושלא בפני בית דין מפי עצמו, bifnei Beit
Din veshelo bifnei Beit Din mipi atzmo, if you did it yourself,
even not in the presence of the court. Okay? אבל מפי אחרים,
aval mipi acherim, if somebody imposed it on you, אין חייבין עד
שיכפרו בהם בבית דין. ein chayavin ad sheyichperu bahem beBeit Din. You
have to have בית דין. It's like it's only in the presence
of the court. Okay, so שבועת העדות, shvuat haedut, if it's imposed
by others, only if it's done by the court. דברי רבי מאיר,
divrei Rabbi Meir, or in the presence of the court. That's what
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. ותניא בברייתא, vetanya beBaraita, fine, so according
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you need it in the presence of
the court imposed by others, שבועת העדות. shvuat haedut. But a ברייתא
Baraita teaches שבועת העדות כיצד? shvuat haedut keitzad? אמר לעדים בואו והעידוני,
amar leedim bou veheiduni,
come testify for me. שבועה שאין אנו יודעים לך עדות, shavuah sheein
anu yodim lecha edut, no, we don't know any testimony. או שאמרו
אין אנו יודעים לך עדות, o sheamru ein anu yodim lecha edut,
or they didn't say a שבועה, they just said we don't know
any testimony.
משביע אני עליכם, mashbia ani aleichem, I make you, I impose an
oath on you to that effect, ואמרו אמן, veamru Amen, and they
said אמן. Amen. בין בפני בית דין בין שלא בפני בית דין,
bein bifnei Beit Din bein shelo bifnei Beit Din, whether it's in
the presence of the court or not. בין מפי עצמו בין מפי
אחרים, bein mipi atzmo bein mipi acherim, and whether they did it
themselves, they said we take a שבועה, or you said take a
שבועה and they said אמן. Amen. כיון שכפרו בהם חייבים, keivan shekachfru
bahem chayavim, if they basically rejected their knowledge of it, they're חייב.
chayav. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says. Now we've got a problem. In the first case רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir said only if you're imposed by others, only in
the presence of a court. This case says even if it's imposed
by others, you're חייב, chayav, right? You see how the same רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying even imposed by others you're חייב chayav
even not in the presence of a court? So how do you
reconcile it? קשיא אהדדי? kashya ahadadei? אלא שמע מינה, ela shma mina,
הא דענה אמן הא דלא ענה אמן. ha deana Amen ha delo
ana Amen. שמע מינה. shma mina. The case he says where it's
not in the presence of the court that somebody imposed it on
you, he explicitly describes it that they said אמן. Amen. Okay, so
the basic point is אמן Amen is not מפי אחרים. mipi acherim.
Somebody else initiated it, but when the words אמן Amen came out
of your mouth, we define that effectively as מפי עצמו. mipi atzmo.
You said it yourself. So when רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says imposed
by somebody else has to be in the presence of a court,
that means if you don't say אמן. Amen.
Okay, but if
the בית דין holds you to court and, you know, we're making
you swear, you don't say
anything, it's effective anyway, which is a חידוש. chiddush. Like you'd think
you need some acquiescence. Okay, but anyway, so that itself is a
חידוש chiddush we'll worry about. But when you say אמן, Amen, that's
like you said it yourself and therefore that works even outside of
a court. And that's how to reconcile רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Similarly,
אמר רבינא משמיה דרבא, Amar Ravina mishmei deRava, מסייעא ליה דהכא נמי
דיקא, mesayeya lei dehacha nami dika, that's also the implication of our
משנה. Mishnah דקתני, dekatani, שבועת ביטוי, נוהגת באנשים ובנשים ברחוקים ובקרובים בכשרים
ובפסולים בפני בית דין ושלא בפני בית דין מפי עצמו. noheget beanshim
ubenashim berachokim ubekrovim bechsherim ubifsulim bifnei Beit Din veshelo bifnei Beit Din
mipi atzmo. It said שבועת ביטוי is only as if you say
it yourself. So the implication is מפי עצמו אין מפי אחרים לא,
mipi atzmo in mipi acherim lo, that was clearly the implication in
the beginning of the משנה, Mishnah that you had to say it
yourself. וקתני סיפא, vekatani seifa, and the end of it says זה
וזה מושבע מפי אחרים חייב, zeh vezeh mushba mipi acherim chayav, that
if you're doing, if you're imposed by others, you're חייב. chayav. So
make up your mind! First you said you have to do it
yourself, then you said by others. קשיא אהדדי, kashya ahadadei, it's contradictory.
אלא שמע מינה, ela shma mina, הא דענה אמן הא דלא ענה
אמן. ha deana Amen ha delo ana Amen. Obviously the answer is
that in the case in the end when it says if somebody
imposes you're חייב, chayav, it's only if you say אמן, Amen, which
is the example the משנה Mishnah gives. Like the משנה Mishnah gives
the example that somebody said אמן, Amen, right? The משנה Mishnah says
ואמר אמן חייב. veamar Amen chayav. So the point of the משנה
Mishnah, is that saying אמן Amen constitutes saying it yourself. אלא שמואל
מאי קא משמע לן? Ela Shmuel mai ka mashma lan? So it's
so obvious from the משנה Mishnah. and from the whatever, what's שמואל
teaching us? דיוקא דמתניתין קא משמע לן. diuka dematnitin ka mashma lan.
He's teaching us how to closely read the משנה, that this הלכה
halacha is present if you pay attention to a close reading of
the משנה. I should say that רמב"ם Rambam actually uses this in
a different area in הלכות ברכות. Hilchot Brachot. רמב"ם Rambam, says the
following, you
know... Listening to a
ברכה bracha is like you said it.
What does it mean like you responded? So רמב"ם Rambam, creates two
levels. He says, כל העונה אמן כמוציא ברכה מפיו דמי. kol ha'oneh
amen k'motzi bracha mipiv dami. If I make a ברכה, bracha, ברוך
אתה ה' אלוהינו מלך העולם שהכל נהיה בדברו, Baruch Atah Adonai Eloheinu
Melech ha'olam shehakol nihiyeh bidvaro, and you say אמן, amen, that אמן
amen is a short version of like you said all those words
that I just said. Okay, so that's כמוציא ברכה מפיו דמי. k'motzi
bracha mipiv dami. It's like you actually said it. והשומע הרי זה
כעונה. vehashome'a harei zeh k'oneh. So if you hear and don't respond,
the word עונה oneh for רמב"ם means it's not like you said
it. It's like you said אמן. amen. So there אמן amen is
like you said it. Listening is like you said אמן. amen. It's,
you know, it's two degrees removed.
But in both he's יוצא, yotzei, in both he's יוצא? yotzei? No,
but according to the רמב"ם, and the question is what's the halachic
difference between כמוציא ברכה מפיו דמי k'motzi bracha mipiv dami or not?
But it's a really nice read of the word כעונה k'oneh and
it creates this level. You could be יוצא yotzei the ברכה bracha
without saying it's like you said it, and you could actually say
the word אמן amen and that's like you actually said the ברכה.
bracha. Okay, so two very nice sort of gradations there according to
רמב"ם, which he obviously gets from this גמרא.